<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title>James Bloomer</title>
    <link href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/"/>
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/atom.xml"/>
    <updated>2014-02-08T13:06:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name>James Bloomer</name>
        <email>james.bloomer@thebloomers.co.uk</email>
    </author>

    
    <entry>
        <id>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/23/fighting-the-darkness</id>
        <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/23/fighting-the-darkness.html"/>
        <title>Fighting The Darkness</title>
        <published>2013-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</published>
        <updated>2013-10-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>James Bloomer</name>
            <uri>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;...or The Importance Of Mid-Winter Festivals In Countries Not Near The Equator&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live in England, which means that come Autumn darkness slides into to my life, the daylight hours shortening with each passing day. I know it&amp;#39;s not as extreme as some other countries but in midwinter it will be dark at 8am and at 4pm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays the start of Autumn feels like a trap closing in. It&amp;#39;s as if some devious thief is stealing my sunshine, draining the energy from my life. The rest of the natural world responds, mainly, in a sensible manner... going to sleep, but we humans carry on. Our environment will not constrain us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was younger the arrival of shorter days never seemed to bother me. What I remember most from those dark nights was solely the change in environment when playing in the evening. In Summer we were out in the street with the other kids, come Winter we were inside, me and my brother inventing games to play in the house to keep us amused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a glimmer of hope... there in mid-winter, beyond Bonfire Night, deep in the darkness there was always Christmas. Christmas meant decorations, lights, family, presents! It meant school plays and Christmas parties. It meant a couple of weeks off school. It meant a huge family meal then watching a film on television and then playing a boardgame. It was the beacon in the middle of the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days I realise the importance of Christmas, not as a religious festival, but as a mid-Winter festival. To me it&amp;#39;s a celebration of the Winter solstice. A celebration of making it half way through the darkness (as The Doctor once said). It is a clever social construct providing us a focus and a hook to pull us through the Autumn, a long ago learned psychological trick. It&amp;#39;s no surprise that a lot of cultures have a festival some time around mid-winter, I think we need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Winter, despite January and February usually being the coldest months in England, everything seems a little bit easier. The days get longer, the nights shrink away. Spring is coming and nothing can stop it. I visualise it as rolling down the other side of a hill, racing towards the summer months and dreamy long days of sunshine and happiness. Of course, the reality of Summer in England is another story...&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <id>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/19/I-see-helicopters-I-think-monsters</id>
        <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/19/I-see-helicopters-I-think-monsters.html"/>
        <title>I See Helicopters, I Think Monsters</title>
        <published>2013-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
        <updated>2013-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>James Bloomer</name>
            <uri>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My life has Science Fiction interwoven through the entirety of its accumulated strata. From seeing Star Wars when I was four years old, to reading Neuromancer and Snow Crash as a teenager, through starting a blog entirely about Science Fiction, to now when Science Fiction is everywhere, on TV, on Film, audio, literature, comics...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So perhaps it is no surprise what I&amp;#39;m about to tell you? Perhaps it is an indication of someone who has spent too much time in imaginary worlds? You can judge yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I live not very far away from an RAF base which is home to helicopters. Consequently when driving around the area, often on the way to work, I will see a helicopter flying across the sky. They&amp;#39;re not small those RAF helicopters, big grey hulking machines cutting through the blue sky, flying impossibly over the green hills. If you think about it too much they seem strange at the best of times. My brain however transposes a Science Fiction overlay onto reality and I imagine that I&amp;#39;m in the film Monsters. Those scenes at the start of the film, the aliens are attacking, the air force is in the sky, the country is in chaos, our hero is embroiled in something... That.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are no monsters. I do not live in a war zone. The helicopters are not attacking anyone, they&amp;#39;re going about their business in a peaceful manner. They traverse to the horizon serenely and uninterrupted and my day returns to the mundane after a few moments of Science Fiction imagination. A jolt of sensawunda injected into my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lifted by moments of Science Fiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the endless dystopias and escapist stories Science Fiction is full of hope. It is proof that we can think about our issues, extrapolate, discuss, forge a different path. Science Fiction is our choices laid before before us. We can learn, we can be better. It starts with adventure and excitement, it leads to deeper thought.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <id>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/14/the-adventures-of-munchines-man</id>
        <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/14/the-adventures-of-munchines-man.html"/>
        <title>The Adventures Of Munchies Man</title>
        <published>2013-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
        <updated>2013-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>James Bloomer</name>
            <uri>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On my way to work, almost every day, I drive past a young man wearing a sandwich board advertising a café called Munchies. I call him Munchies man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes he&amp;#39;s standing by the traffic lights. 
Sometimes he is several miles along the straight, featureless road that passes the power station. 
Sometimes he is struggling to walk a greyhound with the sandwich board clacking around his legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always he looks miserable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often wonder what Munchies Man does for the rest of the day. Does he just wander around in the morning and then head back to the café to server customers over lunch? Does he dump his sandwich board (and optional greyhound), don a suit and while away the day in boardroom meetings? Or does he wander, endlessly, forever doomed to being a walking advertisement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d quite like it if he had another life, a superhero life. If he was a doctor or a fireman. If at a moments notice he could transform into a heroic figure. If perhaps it wasn&amp;#39;t misery on his face every morning but a deep zen-like concentration preparing for the deeds ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m tempted sometimes to stop and ask him, but always resist (not just because of the traffic pressing behind me) but also because of the joy of mystery. Of the possibilities I can imagine for his life. Possibilities that would collapse suddenly should I ever talk to him. A small conversation and no longer the hero in the continuing adventures of Munchies Man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead I watch him every day, for the quick seconds I can see him as I drive past, and wonder about his life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    
    <entry>
        <id>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/11/clouds</id>
        <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://www.jamesbloomer.com/2013/10/11/clouds.html"/>
        <title>Clouds</title>
        <published>2013-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
        <updated>2013-10-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
        <author>
            <name>James Bloomer</name>
            <uri>http://www.jamesbloomer.com/</uri>
        </author>
        <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For most of my early life clouds were a far away feature, a distant part of the sky. I grew up in the middle of England with no mountains around me and hills only maybe a hundred metres tall. I&amp;#39;d look up and there would be clouds but I had no concept of how high they were or what they consisted of. They just were. Sometimes there would be fog or mist, but that was something different, a different feature of the weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The height of clouds was one of the first things that struck me when I moved to Geneva. Driving out from the city towards CERN the Jura lie ahead, not massive mountains for the region but bigger than anything I&amp;#39;d ever been used to. It was immediately obvious if the clouds were a certain height, they&amp;#39;d cut off the tops of the hills. That was a revelation to me. Suddenly clouds were not a remote part of the world above me but right there, interacting with my physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course after a while this becomes normality and sight of the cloud shrouded Jura was something I barely acknowledged. It doesn&amp;#39;t seem to take too long to become accustomed to something, to adjust to a new normality. Then, when I moved back to England, eventually the sight of clouds covering hills faded to a distant memory...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until the other week when the tops of the cooling towers of the power station I drive past every day were cloaked in low cloud. It made me think of the Jura, made me think of the clouds, made me think of the times when I&amp;#39;ve been up mountains with clouds below me. It sparked a little moment of wonder within me, a moment when I really appreciated the world around me and I actually looked at the clouds rather than take them for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wouldn&amp;#39;t it be nice if we could turn on those moments of wonder more frequently and look at the world around us afresh? Perhaps I need to be a little more observant and those moments might come more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
    

</feed>
